ILGWU. Alan Howard papers, 5780/206
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU. Alan Howard papers
1970-1997.
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Howard, Alan.
5780/206
6 cubic feet
6 linear feet
Records
Country files include correspondence and notes, printed material, and newspaper clippings on countries in which the ILGWU had a special interest, especially the Dominican Republic and Honduras. Company files include correspondence, memoranda, notes, and press material on companies with which the ILGWU dealt; especially well-documented is the strike against and negotiations with Leslie Fay. Subject files include correspondence with and collected printed material on labor leaders and politicians, as well as on subjects relating to the garment industry and trade.
6766700
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
June 2011
EAD encoding:
Cheryl Beredo, June 2011
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was founded in New York City in 1900 by mostly Socialist immigrant workers who sought to unite the various crafts in the growing women's garment industry. The union soon reflected changes in the sector and rapidly organized thousands of unskilled and semi-skilled women, mostly Jewish and Italian young immigrants. Exemplifying the "new unionism," the ILGWU led two of the most widespread and best-known industrial strikes of the early Twentieth Century: the shirtwaist makers' strike of 1909 in New York City and the cloak makers' strike of 1910 in Chicago. The union also tried to adapt to the fragmented and unstable nature of the industry. It adopted the "protocol of peace," a system of industrial relations that attempted to ensure stability and limit strikes and production disruption by providing for an arbitration system to resolve disputes.
The ILGWU exemplified the European-style social unionism of its founding members. They pursued bread and butter issues but provided educational opportunities, benefits, and social programs to union members as well. In 1919, the ILGWU became the first American union to negotiate an unemployment compensation fund that was contributed to by its employers. The ILGWU also pioneered in the establishment of an extremely progressive health care program for its members which included not only regional Union Health Centers but also a resort for union workers, known as Unity House. The Union also had an imaginative and pioneering Education Department which not only trained workers in traditional union techniques, but provided courses in citizenship and the English language.
David Dubinsky, an immigrant from Belarus who came to the US in 1911, provided strong leadership that led to unprecedented growth in the union during his presidency from 1932 to 1966. He led the union through successful internal anti-communist struggles, built on the ascendancy of industrial unionism by encouraging the formation of the Committee for Industrial Organization, and helped the union become an important political force in New York City and state politics, and in the national Democratic Party and Liberal Party as well.
In the period following the Second World War, the union suffered a decline in membership as manufacturers avoided unionization and took advantage of less expensive labor by moving shops from the urban centers in the northeast to the south, and later abroad. The ethnic and racial character of the ILGWU also changed as European immigrants were supplanted by Asians, Latin Americans, African- Americans, and immigrants from the Caribbean.
In July 1995 the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) at a joint convention, forming UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees). At the time the new union had a membership of about 250,000 in the United States, Canada, and Puerto Rico.
Biographical / Historical
Alan Howard was Assistant to the President of the ILGWU.
Scope and Contents
Country files include correspondence and notes, printed material, and newspaper clippings on countries in which the ILGWU had a special interest, especially the Dominican Republic and Honduras. Company files include correspondence, memoranda, notes, and press material on companies with which the ILGWU dealt; especially well-documented is the strike against and negotiations with Leslie Fay. Subject files include correspondence with and collected printed material on labor leaders and politicians, as well as on subjects relating to the garment industry and trade.
Conditions Governing Access
The ILGWU Records, except for publications and materials produced for publication, are restricted. Materials created prior to twenty years from the current date are open to researchers only with prior written permission from the Director of the Kheel Center; materials created during the past twenty-years are closed; the minutes of the General Executive Board are closed. For more information contact the Kheel Center.
Related Materials
6000/029. UNITE. Alan Howard. Assistant to the President. Files
General
"Permanent deposit"
Arrangement
Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State); Clothing trade -- New York (State); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; Howard, Alan; Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union --Archives; Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees
6766700
- Series I. Country files
  - Bangladesh/Pakistan, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Caracus, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Canada, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chile, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Costa Rica, 1990-1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cuba, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dominican Republic: Bibong Apparel, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dominican Republic: Bibong Apparel, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dominican Republic: Bilateral Negotiations, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Dominican Republic: Centro de Investigacion Para la Accion Femenina (CIPAF), 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Dominican Republic: Centro de Investigacion Para la Accion Femenina (CIPAF), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Dominican Republic: Clips from Confederacion Nacional de Trabajadores Dominicanos (CNTD), 1988- 1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Dominican Republic: Confederacion Nacional de Trabajadores Dominicanos (CNTD), Internal, 1991- 1995 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Dominican Republic: Confederacion Nacional de Trabajadores Dominicanos (CNTD)/Union de Trabajadores Latino-Americanos (UTLA), 1992 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Dominican Republic: Confederacion Nacional de Trabajadores Dominicanos (CNTD) Delegation, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Dominican Republic: Data, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Dominican Republic: Federacion Nacional de Trabajadores de Zonas Francas (FENATRAZONAS), 1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Dominican Republic: Generalized System of Preferences (GSP) Review, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Dominican Republic: Generalized System of Preferences (GSP) Review, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Dominican Republic: Generalized System of Preferences (GSP) Review, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Dominican Republic: Generalized System of Preferences (GSP) Documents, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Dominican Republic: Generalized System of Preferences (GSP) Documents, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Dominican Republic: Generalized System of Preferences (GSP) Documents, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Dominican Republic: Gomez, Francisco Pena, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Dominican Republic: Han Chang Manufacture Textil Dominica, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Dominican Republic: Servicio Judicial, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - El Salvador, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - El Salvador: Maquilas, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - El Salvador: United States Trade Representative, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Guatemala, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Guatemala, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Guatemala: Generalized System of Preferences (GSP), 1994 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Guatemala: Guatemala Labor Education Project (GLEP), 1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Guatemala: Guatemala Labor Education Project (GLEP), 1995 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Haiti, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Haiti, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Haiti, 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Haiti, 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Honduras, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Honduras, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Honduras, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Honduras, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Honduras, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Honduras/Fesitradeh, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Honduras: Price Waterhouse, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Honduras: trip (Liz Claiborne), 1994 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Honduras: United States Trade Representative, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - India, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Israel: National Committee for Labor Israel (David Dinkins Tribute), 1995 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Mexico, 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Mexico, 1992-1995 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Mexico, 1992-1995 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Scope and Contents
    Clippings
  - Puerto Rico, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Puerto Rico: Section 936, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    United States Tax Code
  - Saipan, 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Taiwan, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Thailand, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Series II. Company files
  - Cynge Designs, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Dayton Hudson Corporation, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Eddie Bauer, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Esprit, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Gitano, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Kellwood, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Koret, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Kunja Knitting Mills, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Leslie Fay, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Leslie Fay, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Leslie Fay, current, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Leslie Fay,current, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Leslie Fay Congressional Hearing, June 7, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Congressional Hearing on the Future of Leslie Fay and the Domestic Apparel Industry, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Congressional Hearing on the Future of Leslie Fay and the Domestic Apparel Industry, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Leslie Fay ( Hearing of the Subcommittee on Labor Management Relations, July 21), 1994 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Leslie Fay, Guatemala, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Leslie Fay, Guatemala, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Leslie Fay, Honduras, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - International Ladies Garment Workers' Union: Leslie Fay, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Leslie Fay, international overview, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Leslie Fay, leaflets, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Leslie Fay, liquidated damages, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Leslie Fay, Macy's, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Leslie Fay, post-strike, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Leslie Fay, press coverage, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Leslie Fay, reading material, 1992-1994 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Stakeholders Alliance Report, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Leslie Fay
  - Leslie Fay, visuals, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Photos
  - Leslie Fay, X, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Confidential
  - Maidenform, 1992-1994 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Phillips-Van Heusen, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Phillips Van-Heusen, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Sara Lee, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Warnaco, 1992-1995 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Series III. Subject files
  - Administrative (expenses, etc.), 1992-1994 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Codes of Conduct, Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) Contract, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO) Executive Council, 1993- 1995 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO) International Organizing and Solidarity Sub-Committee, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO) International Organizing and Solidarity Sub-Committee, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO), miscellany, 1993- 1994 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    statements, campaign updates
  - American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO), politics, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO), trade, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - American Institute for Free Labor Development (AIFLD), 1994 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - American Institute for Free Labor Development (AIFLD), 1995 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - American Institute for Free Labor Development (AIFLD), August 26, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - American Institute for Free Labor Development (AIFLD), Dominican Republic, January 5, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Angelo, Alfred, 1993-1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General Archives, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Brochure, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Caribbean Basin Initiative (CBI), 1995 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Contracts, 1993-1995 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Chavez, Cesar, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Memorial Celebration
  - Child Labor, 1970-1994 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Clinton, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    President-elect
  - Clinton/International Ladies Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU), 1992 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Clinton, news conferences, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Conference on the Future of the American Workplace, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Conference on the Future of the American Workplace, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - D'Amato, Alfonse (Senator), 1992 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Daily News/Chinatown, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Damon/Amerimex/Mexico, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Damon/Amerimex/Mexico, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Dinkins, David, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Mayor of New York City
  - Donahue, Tom, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO), Secretary-Treasurer
  - Economy, taxes,etc., 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Education reform (Box 4, Folder 21)
    No date
  - Fair Trade Campaign, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Federacao Internacional dos Trabalhadores do Textil, Vestuario, Couro, Calcado/ Organizacan Regional Interamericana (FITTVCC/ORI), 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Financial Records, 1993-1996 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Firm Analysis Working Group, 1992-1995 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Florida/Miscellaneous, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Free Trade Zones (FTZ), Asia, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Freedom House, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT), 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT), 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT), 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - General Executive Board (GEB) Meetings, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Hart Survey, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    International Ladies Garment Workers' Union members
  - Howard, Alan to Mazur, Jay, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    Memos
  - In These Times, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Inside Edition, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Industrial Strategy, 1992-1994 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Industrial Union Department, labor law reform, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Industrial Union Department, labor law reform, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Industry data and analysis, 1992-1994 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Inter-Church Center for Corporate Responsibility (ICCR), 1993 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - International Labor Organization, 1993-1995 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - International Labor Rights Education and Research Fund, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - International Organizing and Solidarity Committee, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - International Organizing and Solidarity Committee, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - International Organizing and Solidarity Committee, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - International Strategy, 1992-1994 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Jokes, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Kantor, Mickey, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    United States Trade Representative
  - Kearney, Neil, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    International Textile, Garment and Leather Worker's Federation (ITGLWF) General Secretary
  - Kernaghan, Charles, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Kernaghan, Charles, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Kirkland, Lane, 1992-1995 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO), President
  - Kirkland, Lane, 1992-1995 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Labor law reform, 1992-1994 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Labor law reform, 1992-1994 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Labor trends, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Layoffs, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Letters to editors, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Magali. Pineda, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    Centro de Investigacion para la Accion Femenina (CIPAF)
  - Mazur, Jay on North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA), 1993 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Miscellany, 1993-1995 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - National Labor Committee, Charles Kernaghan, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Negotiations/Communications, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - New York, economic development, 1992-1993 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - New York City, industry development, 1992-1995 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Report of the Administration on North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA), 1992 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Overseas Private Investment Corporation, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Political Contacts, base, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Productivity Advisory Council, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - References, 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Romney, Edgar, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - San Francisco, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Starobin, Herman, 1991-1995 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Starobin, Herman, 1991-1995 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Trade, 1992-1994 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    essays, speeches
  - Trade/strategy, 1992-1995 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - "Trade Game" poster, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Triangle Fire Commemoration Speeches, 1993-1995 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    Mazur, Jay
  - Tyler, Gus, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - United States Trade Representative, 1992-1993 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Walmart, 1992-1993 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Yale Political Forum, 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 21)